all right hello everyone it is
July 11th and we're in the second
discussion on chapter two
so before we go into any of the
questions
does anyone just want to bring up
anything or just start with anything
about chapter two
um Ali and then anyone else who raised
their hands
uh thank you yeah I just uploaded uh the
equation to 0.5 walkthrough uh in the
um I guess I put it in the equations
table if I'm not mistaken but equation
2.6 needs a little bit more fine-tuning
before it's ready but uh I'm sure it'll
be ready for the next week so I think I
put it at the top of the
notes section of equation 2.5 so if
anyone wants to
uh
but yeah that's it
foreign
looks awesome can we maybe uh go over it
or can you just walk through it or yeah
sure yeah uh well first of all
um
we began with
um just basic definitions uh such as
some fundamental definitions such as the
Shannon entropy and then to derive uh
the first line we put we substitute the
Shannon entropy term uh into the uh I
mean the first line of equations so uh
and we can see there's uh an interesting
parallel between uh this kind of
formulation between energy and entropy
and also the path integral formulation
and variation of preology but the
essential difference here is that
here the first term represents only the
energy but for the path integral it can
be best described as the energy
constraint uh so that's
um more of a side note there and then
for the second line of equation 2.5
we get but before going into
um
the second line just let me unpack the
first line a little bit more so for for
the people who who are not familiar with
a callback Library Divergence uh we put
the definition of callback library at
the top of the
um
or yeah at the top of the page one and
then uh by using uh James inequality we
get uh the Callback the lighter
Divergence bounded by the expectation
of the log p over q and that allows us
to substitute the Shannon entropy term
into the expectation of the log p over Q
so that was the essential move for
unpacking the first line of equations so
I mean without Jensen's inequality we
wouldn't
exactly get the the exact term of the
first line of the equation because
obviously the order of the log operator
and the expectation operator is
different than uh we need here
so yeah that's basically a
straightforward algebraic manipulation
um
and the the second line of equation 2.5
or you know the terms the trade-off
between complexity and accuracy
similarly can result from
uh substituting uh I mean by expanding
uh the first line of the equation and
then substituting some of the term as
the Callback Library Divergence and then
we get the complexity term uh and the
rest will be the accuracy so this what
it means is that as pointed at the
bottom of the page the greater
complexity is uh in other words the more
one needs to change beliefs to explain
observations the Lesser predictive
accuracy will become so in this case
variational free energy uh would be just
the minimization of the complexity or at
the same time maximizing the accuracy
and again it can be
compared to the path integral
formulation it's almost identical to the
path integral formulation of the
trade-off between complexity and the
accuracy
uh all right so for this for the third
line of equation 2.5
uh we try to somehow get the trade-off
between the Divergence and the evidence
but in this case evidence is just uh
something that acts as
um as the bound or the uh evidence lower
bound uh so it's something that's always
greater than or equal to surprise right
so
by unpacking the
um the last line of equation 2.5 into
these two distinct terms or the this
trade-off between Divergence and
evidence uh we are allowed to have this
um elbow or evidence lower bound or in
other words the negative upper bound
that would enable us to regard BFE as
the optimization parameter uh or over
the parameter to be optimized rather
than uh trying to achieve the exact
value of uh free energy but just some
optimization parameter which would be
much more uh
tractable than trying to achieve the
exact amount of the free image
foreign
work
nice
cool stuff
anyone want to ask a question or or make
a comment on this
could you maybe explain a little more
like zoomed out from this document what
does the variational free energy uh
do in the model like in the textbook
yeah so A variation free energy is
a variational technique that sorry
as I mentioned allows us to do the
approximate computations of Bayesian
inference uh in terms of optimizing a
certain parameter namely the variational
free energy because Computing the exact
Bayesian inference of the orbasian
output sorry Bayesian inference
with regard to both posterior and prior
would be
almost impossible
especially in complicated complicated
situations and by complicated I mean
everything that's not trivialism a
simple situation so that would basically
uh are all real-time situations that we
encounter
um and uh obviously we're interested in
modeling so this this approximate
Bayesian inference technique is a very
useful way to overcome this shortcoming
uh exact Bayesian inference in terms of
its of its intractability and it makes
the computation of or the optimization
of the variation of free energy much
more computable and tractable as
compared to
um exact Bayesian inference uh which
would obviously have uh many practical
um
I mean it can have uh many practical
benefits uh and not just something uh
that's described in theory and doesn't
have any practical applications and
modeling and so on so yeah that's uh
basically the idea behind using the
variational technique and using a
certain parameter as the upper bound or
in other words the negative of a lower
bound
that needs to be optimized whether
maximize or minimized
um instead of just trying to compute the
exact value of Interest
so variation free energy on the other
hand
includes all the
um
established Frameworks for doing
Bayesian inferences so for example the
techniques developed by James Kahneman
and others that I I think it was
um
which table was um which figure I in one
of the figures in the book I I suppose
it was in chapter two I guess uh there's
a nice comparison between uh the
different terms of variation of free
energy and all the other theories of uh
Bayesian inference yeah exactly
so we can see that it's
um more generalized theory of optimizing
the Bayesian inference than risk
sensitive kale control and other
techniques of amazing inference that's
that have been developed throughout I
mean the past several decades and um
so
each of those terms
can be
accounted for
by including or let me put it this way
by vomiting some of the terms and we can
basically get the exact same formulation
or the exact same previous formulations
we had before but as we see this is the
much more uh General way of
um
calculating the approximate Bayesian
inference
okay
Anuj do you want to ask your question or
do you want me to read it
yeah I just had this curious like uh is
that case like when we already know that
uh like I cannot do exact inference that
are there cases when uh I should also
avoid optimizing this variation free
energy given that in any case I cannot
do exact movement
I'll give a first thought on that you
always could you could choose your
models however you want but you will be
doing strictly worse with respect to the
accuracy complexity trade-off
so you could but you can invent an
arbitrary statistical method
but you you will not outperform the um
information geometric
maximum possible
um performance
yeah thank you
in any given free energy that you do
compute
the the model may just be rolling to the
bottom of the hill and you might just be
way off base for a real system
so this isn't the model adequacy
problem
this is the model
optimization problem
so it's analogous to the l-tune norm in
the linear regression framework like
every scatter plot you always converge
to the one L2 Norm
progression r squared p-value all of
this
so this plays a somewhat of an analogous
role
um by enabling these uh different uh
generative models
to be optimized in a real-time
sequential way
and it turns out that it's the same
um optimization strategy that
variational autoencoders use
uh and just variational methods in
physics
so it's not like variational methods
comes from fep or or active
it's just using Bayes optimal model
fitting
just like L2 regression let's just say
is optimal linear regression fitting
optimal base fitting with the
variational free energy
which is a functional
because it's a function of a function
it's a function of Q the function that
you're optimizing over and why the data
that are coming in
so generative model of vision and
sensory incoming data which is what is
like the thing that is is getting
the best trade-off
of accuracy and variance
thank you
okay and then
um
Ali or oh and yeah go for it
uh sorry yeah and one
um I think crucial Point here is uh the
reason for using
um the Callback Library Divergence for
comparing uh the two distributions so uh
I suppose the justification for using KL
Divergence is not explicitly
stated in the textbook but it it
derives from the name in Pearson Lemma
which is basically says something to the
effect that most efficient way to
compare two distributions would be to
compare the logarithm of their I mean to
compute the logarithm of their
likelihood ratios so that's basically
what's meant by callback libler so it's
not just an arbitrary technique for
comparing to this distributions it's
actually a proven theorem or Lemma that
that this is actually actually the most
efficient way to compare two
distributions so uh
yeah I wanted to point that out as well
yeah thanks and just adding one piece
I'll put this in the notes there
this is uh with nor Sajid and others and
Carl
and they use the Rainy Divergence so in
principle
you could use different Divergence or
distance measures
but
the kind of um I mean it's a it's
definitely an interesting question about
where one might have different
properties but KL is kind of like
the go-to in at least this sense
yeah Alexi and then anyone else
this may seem like a silly question I
think Ali gave a fantastic mathematical
uh Road uh but is there a metaphor for
variational free energy versus free
energy that's free energies explained in
the book well the variational cell this
one is intractable this one is tractable
this is an estimation but
uh I don't know in terms of you know uh
is there an example or a metaphor that
can bring it home a variational for
energy specifically does anybody have a
yeah I'll think about it I'm happy to
say one but does anyone else want to
you have a thought like
what is free energy and you know and
variational free energy
how can we think about these
Ali that anyone else who wants to
um yeah I'm not sure about
um particular metaphor but uh you see uh
the I mean the optimization approach as
opposed to calculating the exact value
of something that basically comes
uh or it can be uh likened to the
situation we have uh when uh when very
in a very simple situations uh we have a
function uh that can get an exact value
of something as compared to the
asymptotes of uh getting increasingly uh
close to the to the value but never
reaching the value so uh by optimization
we allow for even uh the exact even for
the situations for for which we don't
have any information uh with which we
would be able to calculate the exact
value of something but instead we can
get closer and closer to the exact value
with the information we have but how but
nonetheless we can reach a very good
approximation and obviously we can
Define uh what is what do we mean by the
good approximation based on uh the error
we we want to reach but uh yeah in most
situations we don't have enough
information to calculate the exact value
of the parameter we want to calculate so
it's more than the question of
intractability versus tractability in
some cases it is uh I mean impossible to
compute the exact value based on the
information we have so
um I believe in these cases the
optimization technique or variational
technique is the only way we can get
close enough to the real value
or to the exact value
that's great
Point
um that like even if the the variational
model is just woefully not structurally
mapping onto the real
external uh generating function
like the generative model is a unimodal
distribution
um and then the the out there in the
world there's like five bins
and so then there would be different
patterns of model fit like it might just
fit the one that has the most or the one
not the most or blur the whole thing but
according to its generative model
it would never get worse in terms of
all of the considerations in equation
2.5
it will never get worse on the
complexity minus accuracy Frontier or it
will learn that trade-off manifold
optimally
so those are some fairly
um
good statistical uh aspects just of any
Bayesian model that's fit this way
so that doesn't guarantee like adequacy
in the real world because again you
could just have an inadequate generative
model then cease to get to the charging
station or whatever
um so it's not a success or a function
guarantee but it's a model fit
or it doesn't mean that you'll have um
adequately balanced
you know or had a memory window that's
optimal or all these other things unless
you've really taken them all into
account
and and then just to Alexi's question uh
or Broadway do you want to add anything
um
equation 2.6 is the expected for energy
I'll leave maybe do you want to
summarize how is equation 2.5 different
than 2.6
Yeah so basically
um they're very very similar
structurally uh but uh obviously we need
to take into account uh the pi or the
policy that needs to be
um I mean in variation free energy we we
only deal with the situation in which uh
the perceptual data is
um we only deal with perceptual data so
we don't need to uh
act upon the environment in order to fit
the data better to our generative model
but in expected free energy
we delve into the action domain of the
I mean action perception so obviously in
this case we need to take into account
uh the effect of the policies on our
both priors and posteriors so uh the
point of commencement uh for for
derivation of equation 2.6 from equation
to 0.5 is exactly how applying
the policies to those prior and
posterior terms can affect uh the whole
equation and that's where we get
equation 2.6 and its uh variance in
other lines of the equation
awesome
one point about equation 2.6 is uh first
off it's G not f
and it is uh like the argument that it
takes is pi which is the vector of the
list of all of the policy trajectory
possibilities
so variational free energy which was
described
um really comprehensively earlier is
basically that trade-off Frontier
um between accuracy and variance
estimator
according to a generative model that's
the Q and the Y on the variational free
energy this is like a sense making or
perceptual real time and the
self-evidencing component of variational
free energy is like if you're repeatedly
measuring your body to be at homeostasis
and you expect and prefer that then like
things are working out and that's sort
of the closure
of the adoptive organism is like by
fitting the variational free energy
about homeostasis
then it stays within homeostatic bound
but expected free energy uses this pie
or policy variable
and so
whereas variational free energy is more
like signals processing expected free
energy is more like control theory
because it's an explicit evaluation
of
different possible futures
does anyone have any other like thoughts
or or ways of thinking about
variational and expected free energy
um
I did have a this is more of a form of
question sorry but uh I thought it might
be useful so
we have here in chapter two page 34.
um when evaluating the free energy of
outcomes the outcomes are the
consequences however when evaluating the
expected free energy the outcomes play
the role of causes and since they're
variables that are in the future but
explain decisions of the present
um would you say that everything you
said this far is kind of
gotten to that
um kind of explaining what that quote
means
maybe paste the quote here just so we
can see it
thank you meanwhile
let's let's uh look at this
question can anyone throw some light on
these terms both are posterior so indeed
sometimes like the like initial prior D
is called like the prior but technically
every variable that gets an observation
coming to it in a Bayesian framework
is a prior an observation in a posterior
update on something it's not like a
free-floating prior so every
distribution that's Bayesian
that's why it's like prior on state
space
or prior on policy which is like habit
that gets sharpened by expected free
energy so then the output of this
operation is like
habit
the policy prior sharpened by g into
policy posterior
and then that policy posterior can be
sampled from or just selected with the
best option
um then about the um specific
interests you paste it in all um we'll
look at it but just now to these two
terms mentioned so Q x given pi and Q x
given Y and Pi so this is a question
about the KL Divergence
um so
the the
computation of the expected free energy
for a given policy
everything is conditioned on like that
policy happening and so between these
two things uh two sides of the double
line
they're both conditional policy and
they're both have an aboutness of the
Hidden State Through Time X tilde so the
only difference is that there's that
there's this y tilde observations
Through Time on the left side so if the
observations that you expect under that
course of action
aren't going to update your hidden State
beliefs
then the the Divergence between these
two cues is zero the information is
meaningless there's no information
gained
you're not learning anything you're not
updating your hidden State model
based upon the observation whereas if it
was a epistemically informative course
of action and do you expect it to reduce
your uncertainty
um on this course of action
then y tilde
would lead to an update on X tilde so
there would be a Divergence here
so that policy would have epistemic
value
whereas the pragmatic value
is about the alignment of preferences
with the observations that you expect
all right
does anyone have a thought on or or on
on this quote from Andrew
I'll just give one reading not sure if
this is the the full um or only way
which is like
um
when we're talking about the uh the
sensory data themselves which are some
sometimes just called outcomes sensory
outcomes
so like when we're talking about
the the why that were
um the outcomes that we're actually
observing
um those are the consequences of hidden
states that are like emitting those
so we're doing we're doing equation 2.5
um where the consequences of the causal
model
are what we're trying to fit
um in contrast in 2.6 those observations
in why tilde have not happened yet
so they're projected
observations
so they are um unobserved like it's not
it's the opposite of time travel say you
and I haven't observed the temperature
in two hours
but I can have a tight or or a wide uh
prior on is that variable but it's um
it's a type of hidden cause analysis
to say well if this happens under this
condition
and then basically kind of back
propagate that into the present
so as a causal impact of an
informational State that's expected
and that's not like a paradox or
anything like that
but so there are the outcomes of a
causal process but then in the efe
they also have a causal
Force because differences in them lead
to differences different differences in
expected observations lead to different
action selection
anyone else want to ask a question or it
looks like there's at least one that's
from the cohort
Alexi yeah
um so I was really uh
happy to to read this paragraph where
they talk about generative process and
generated model and they're saying that
uh they could be in different state
spaces one could be five dimensional one
could be two-dimensional continuous and
categorical I think that's a very
profound statement uh and
uh for example if I talk about
temperature outside and I use words
and I see things like hot and cold right
so I I place a continuous
outside variable in my two categories so
I could model this way but it's it's a
bit of a distortion if you wish
but I don't know if you have any
comments I'm just thinking out loud
about this that
this this is this is a thing it's just
mind-blowing that you know we're
modeling something but we will be in a
completely different state space and
different variables different variable
structure right
yeah that's a great Insight uh one thing
I'd add to that is like
um if you measure the the
height of the people in the classroom
you can optimize a binary classifier
tall or short
and then you can do optimal model fit to
make the the line between tall and short
you know optimize some trade-off
like recall or something like that
accuracy Mouse complexity you could do
three category model four category model
you can do a continuous model all these
statistical distributions and like
they're all gonna not complain they're
all gonna get optimized
so that's kind of the the blindness but
the power of
essentially just Bayesian statistics is
that once it's all lined up
it just is going to get optimized now it
may be hard to optimize it maybe easy
again it may be adequate or not
but it's kind of like within so so
just that um
yeah
it just this is what the the the
strengths and the weaknesses of
empirical modeling
which is that modeling doesn't have to
reflect
the structure of the modeled system
at all
um and it doesn't for scientists and it
doesn't for the models that are made
but some of them are adaptive still so
those are the lifelike ones but
pedagogically they don't have to be
lifelike
that's a very great example it helps and
one more question if I may and then I'll
be silent at the end of the chapter they
use the word intention you know and I
posted in the chat the the exact quote
where they say in psychological terms
this implies that preachers believe
about policies directly corresponds to
its intention
which it fulfills by acting right
I'm just a little puzzled by the use of
the word intention which typically means
motive
of an agent you know
um I don't know how it's meant here this
is where I got a little lost and what
exactly do they mean by intention here
seems an unconventional use of the trend
anyone want to give a thought on that
okay
I uh
oh yeah go for it
uh yeah this is just a speculation but
um maybe
um the meaning of the word intention
here and particularly in this paragraph
uh is related to the way it's used in um
some of some of the literature on action
philosophy so for instance
Alicia Juarez has developed a theory of
intention as a kind of
the process that results from the
causation of constraints so by intention
uh she means basically the process that
puts the system of interest in its
causal constraints so it's not
necessarily
um
maps onto or at least precisely maps
onto the psychological sense of the term
so but that's just as I said only in a
speculative thinking I may be wrong
okay another
um angle is from the paper
um active inference models do not
contradict folk psychology
it was live stream 46. does anyone who
participated in that or was there want
to just like summarize what they thought
this paper's argument was about that
issue
so basically they use the belief desire
intention framework BDI
um which I I had not heard of but it's a
commonly used framework
um and it actually came up in the first
lecture by aval in the um active
inference for the social sciences Ben
White
mentioned folks psychology and aval kind
of like followed up was like what do you
mean by like by by this basically but
the belief desire intention models just
widely used to explain
everyday behavior and intentionality
it's like what people kind of slip to
um you know this enzyme wants to bind to
this or you know prefers to bind to this
in a way just kind of broadly and they
identified those constructs belief
desire and intention
um with different constructs in the
active inference generative model
so they just basically said like
you're not wrong it just it just it's
just a description
but they uh but the beliefs are the
hidden state
beliefs
um and uh
they kind of unpack this in the context
of uh also distinguishing between
the discrete time active inference
um chapter seven and the continuous time
active inference chapter eight
and so they kind of do simulations that
pull out the
um
belief desire and intention
[Music]
pieces
um in the context of someone who's going
to the fridge
and getting ice cream
which Gene had a field day with
um yeah but but another more
deflationary way not necessarily like an
experienced intentionality like the set
point of a thermostat
or the set point of a motor
limb
you can call it what you and it's just
as long as you understand the map of
territory then such an intentionality is
is not
massively metaphysical
I I found the use of the word intention
there just so like from within the
confines of the models to described as
far as chapter to just be referring to
like we're including a c uh Vector that
is preferences like those are included
along the way like there's a yeah
something like desire or some kind of
you know direction that agent is heading
as opposed to just total free form
you know going for anything right
yeah
good point about how these um intentions
or preferences or um expectations uh for
for observe observed outcomes
that those form kind of like explicit
intentions
like if you have in terms of the
directionality and the amplitude
and uh
and yeah there's a lot to say on on that
but this is what goal oriented or
um adaptive Behavior
would look like
not saying that every single
um implementation of such a system is
like you know or taking on any of that
like we don't
really talk about reward
um or goal in the active ontology
so that's why some people have very um
broad views on like intentionality and
action but the deflationary and
instrumental answer is always it's a
variational Bayesian model with action
signal processing plus control theory
Bayesian statistics
dot dot that's not even including free
energy principle or Bayesian mechanics
or going into any of that part at all
so it's purely defensible even without
fep just thought I would say that
foreign
did whoever added this question want to
explain it
um or anyone else who's here want to ask
something just while they're here
Okay so
about equation 2.6 and epistemic value
so value of new information
instead of minimizing the Divergence we
want to select policies that maximize
the expected diversions hence
Information Gain okay so only with
respect to the epistemic value
more
um informative observations is more
epistemic value
that doesn't mean that those highly
informative policies are going to have a
pragmatic value like discovering What's
um at the bottom of the ocean May um
disrupt pragmatic value about your body
temperature
um but it is an epistemic policy
how can we reconcile the above statement
with page six all facets of behavior in
cognition living organisms follow unique
imperative
minimizing the surprise and the
approximate variational free energy of
their sensory observations
anyone have a thought on this
so
models of perception and action
that do surprise minimization have the
best possible generative model
minimization of surprise is equivalent
to maximization of model evidence if you
knew exactly what to expect how much to
expect it
that's the same thing as saying you have
the best fitting model so maximization
model evidence is surprise minimization
that can't be exactly solved that's the
exact phase issue that we discussed
earlier
the most modern way to solve it is
variational accelerated optimization on
the Bayesian evidence lower bound
now you could do that about any variable
in principle
but what this imperative does is it
connects it back to sensory observations
which can be interpreted as for example
homeostatic
so minimizing surprise on homeostatic
variables
minimizing surprise via Fe
of any variable is doing the optimal
Bayesian inference on it
you could do strictly worse on
um accuracy or variance estimation but
you don't if you want to use the phase
optimal phase information Criterion
optimal model this is just how it's done
but this connects it to the homeostatic
potentially adaptive
imperative but it doesn't have to be
seen as like super adaptive and
strategic it can be seen also for like
an inert object
um
that's the variational free energy so
that's the kind of unified imperative of
real-time self-effidencing
Behavior but as was mentioned it does
not address action selection
it's a functional of beliefs cue and the
data y so we need the expected free
energy which is explicitly prospective
now within the expected free energy
there's the two terms of the that
different policies are evaluated based
on epistemic value in the pragmatic
value
such as one of the decompositions that
that I will all look forward to the um
the breakdowns on
but yes it is the case that for a given
evaluation of a policy
the more Divergent the sensory
information are
the higher the epistemic value would be
but that doesn't mean that it would be
associated with
um a pragmatic value
so an adoptive agent would
um you'd hope avoid extremes of both
extreme information seeking that risk
pragmatic value or vice versa
so that's the model fitting questioned
balancing all the parameters so that the
strategies actually adaptive
um
okay
Alexi and then we'll continue with this
question
I wanted to add to what you just said uh
Daniel just a very nice way to summarize
it that
seeking epistemic value seeking
knowledge is for humans pleasurable you
know this is an effective Neuroscience
called the seeking Drive literally the
dopaminergic exploratory system we enjoy
that this is the enthusiasm curiosity
that drives scientists and artists and
other things and when all our biological
needs are met when we're not hungry
anymore when we're safe we default back
to that system we start exploring the
environment around us to see what's out
there to gain epistemic knowledge to
maximize evidence to decrease the
surprise the negative surprise me in the
future
so that we're not killed you know and
we're not dying from Hunger once we
explore the environment and find out
where's the worship and where the
Predators that helps us in the future to
avoid unpleasant surprises
nice
um
so the Divergence for the variational
free energy
let's look at two point well we we've
seen them previously
um
maximizing Divergence to maximize
Information Gain appears logical
however maximizing Information Gain
would maximize ambiguity and risk
which is
um the uncertainty about consequences of
action in the world
and it um or
um
uh this could be describing risk
um in these two lines
which are two very similar
representations of equation 2.6
um like the left term is the same
and here is observations
so this is the risk of like sort of
conditioned on a policy
um about how uncertain their uh how much
uncertainty there is about observation
sequences and here is about hidden
States
and I believe that this number is always
less than this number
because you're always more certain that
proposing something hidden
you're always more uncertain about
I believe there may be a different
reason but it it's like
you're always more uncertain about
proposed latent causes
above and beyond
um
surprise uh bounding of observables
maybe there's another way to think about
that's it
thank you Lexi wooden beliefs assign low
probability to policies
that will maximize discrepancy expected
free energy ambiguity and risk
well kind of yes and no
um
what would be the the most epistemically
salient
would be something where you were sure
about the outcomes
and they were going to contribute to
Information Gain like I have a trusty
book and I know that so I have a hundred
percent certainty about how opening the
book to this page
about kind of like the epistemic quality
so it's a Salient
um and a mapping between
the the underlying semantics and the
observation
so this representation just maybe
there's another way to see it too but or
I mean I'm sure there are but just like
this isn't like Risk like Danger
this is um
as as far as I understand
um looking at
uh
how your action
uh maps cleanly and preferably
and here's the the more sensory mapping
not to get too deep in that one point
but yeah anyone else have any
questions or thoughts on uh chapter two
Ollie that was awesome
um
work how are you gonna continue
uh well we'll continue to unpack uh all
the other at least essential equations
if not uh all the single equations in
the textbook but we're focusing on
uh developing uh similar derivations for
all the central equations in the in the
textbook and particularly from chapters
two three and uh four uh which I believe
uh constitute uh the most uh fundamental
chapters of the textbook so
um I hope we can prepare it in time so
it can be uh hopefully useful for anyone
who wants to unpack the understand them
uh a bit better
awesome
anyone else have any thoughts
well
um
we will head next into chapter three
so
why do we seem to interested only in
discrete State space discrete actions
policy discrete time is fine
yeah
um well chapter eight you're gonna love
but uh it is presented as as um there's
always a
[Music]
um
the screen continuous time are just two
options or two two families of models
that can be hybridized in chapter eight
but yeah 100 the book focuses on both
um and Thomas parr's bookstream
is uh
um
he describes the history and the
differential Focus between continuous
and discrete time models
and it's a big topic that we talk about
in chapter seven and eight
do you have any other information
yeah and even before those chapters that
we encounter uh preliminary formulation
for continuous time active imprints in
chapter four as well
yeah and five with a spinal reflex arc
so
they're just different
and uh I mean the and
the figure 4.3 the kind of Rosetta Stone
figure
is about the structural similarities
between discrete time and continuous
time models
but also understanding their differences
so chapter three is going to be the uh
High Road
so figure 1.2
chapter 2 was the base theorem so that's
why we were talking a lot about like the
fundamentals of Bayesian statistics
because up until this point this is the
same thing as just saying variational
Bays with perception and action
that is exact no someone can
implement the variational Bays with
perception and action differently but
kind of
thinking cybernetically that's what they
would need to make any kind of active
inference agents whether it's you know
using fristonian active inference or
just or not but if it has to perception
in action
chapter three is gonna take a very
different approach
that's not going to um
Focus as much on the how
as on the why
of self-organization
and the way that this is modeled with
different Bayesian architectures
this kind of prepared us on how it's
going to be done chapter 3 is a focus on
the why
and the free energy principle and then
also it's going to arrive at active
inference
chapter 4 is more about the generative
model
discrete time or continuous
chapter five is neurobiology kind of a
sampling of different kinds of
generative models how they connect
so that's kind of the next three
chapters
all right so enjoy everyone thank you
thanks again Ali and um and everyone
else who helps with the math oh yeah
there will be
um math learning groups
I believe there are Wednesdays at 13 UTC
they're on the calendar
um so uh you know whether there's one
person or more than one person
I hope people enjoy studying there and
and connecting and just improve the
documentation do whatever people feel
like doing
um but uh
there's not a specific Focus or a
facilitation around these sessions at
this point but if someone wants to
whether they're familiar with math or
not they're welcome to
um but just good luck in the math
learning group
all right
thank you
bye thanks everyone see ya